<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Josh Brandoff</title>
    <link>http://brandoff.is/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Josh Brandoff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 10:30:33 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://brandoff.is/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>about me</title>
      <link>http://brandoff.is/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 10:30:33 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brandoff.is/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a mathematically-inclined entrepreneur and engineer of biologically-inspired, intelligent, and distributed systems. I was recently the Co-founder and CTO at &lt;a href=&#34;http://wadeandwendy.ai&#34;&gt;Wade &amp;amp; Wendy&lt;/a&gt;, a venture-backed startup in NYC building artificially intelligent personalities that grow real relationships through conversation. Previously, I was a Core Developer at &lt;a href=&#34;http://storj.io/&#34;&gt;Storj&lt;/a&gt;, a Bitcoin-based decentralized storage platform, and the Lead Developer at &lt;a href=&#34;http://harmony-institute.org&#34;&gt;Harmony Institute&lt;/a&gt;, an interdisciplinary research center exploring the science of narrative media. Before that, I was the founding technologist at the National Museum of Mathematics. For several years, I also imported, promoted and distributed a rose-based sweet to every state in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m deeply interested in complex systems, emergent behavior and distributed or decentralized systems and have &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007%2F978-3-642-20760-0_4&#34;&gt;published work&lt;/a&gt; on genetic stigmergy, a biologically-inspired algorithm that supports self-organization of robotic swarms. I&amp;rsquo;ve also studied permaculture design with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.permaculturenewyork.com/&#34;&gt;Andrew Faust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current languages of choice are Clojure, Clojurescript, and Golang. I also dig Python and ES6/ES7-style JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>License</title>
      <link>http://brandoff.is/license/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brandoff.is/license/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;content-license&#34;&gt;Content license&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All non-code blog content is licensed under &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons BY-NC-ND 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-license&#34;&gt;Code license&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All source code files and snippets found on this blog, unless otherwise explicitly noted, are licensed under the terms below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34;&gt;Copyright 2017 Joshua Brandoff

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the &amp;quot;License&amp;quot;);
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an &amp;quot;AS IS&amp;quot; BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A &#39;Mining&#39; System for Decentralized Ride Sharing Networks</title>
      <link>http://brandoff.is/blog/a-mining-system-for-decentralized-ride-sharing-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2015 11:16:59 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brandoff.is/blog/a-mining-system-for-decentralized-ride-sharing-networks/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://brandoff.is/img/neon-and-signs-on-buildings-with-busy-traffic-at-night.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Ride Sharing and Geometric Proof of Work&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fastcoexist.com/3041403/could-lazooz-be-the-ride-sharing-app-weve-been-waiting-for&#34;&gt;read about&lt;/a&gt; a project called &lt;a href=&#34;http://lazooz.org/&#34;&gt;La’Zooz&lt;/a&gt; that aims to truly decentralize the “ride-sharing” industry. Unlike Lyft or Uber, La’Zooz will utilize blockchain and cryptocurrency technologies to support their decentralized network. The token of reward and exchange in the La’Zooz world will be the ‘Zooz’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, La’Zooz allows drivers to “mine” Zooz using a mobile app as long as the app detects that the user is driving around. While I’ll admit that I haven’t dug too deeply into the technicals behind La’Zooz, I feel like there are several potential problems here. If La’Zooz holds a pool of Zooz and rewards driver/miners through individual reporting, malicious users could potentially forge GPS and other sensor data from their mobile devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, because I’m passionate about decentralization and think a truly decentralized drive-sharing platform would be really cool, I decided to think on it a bit and came up with a potential mining and reward system for La’Zooz drivers and “riders” (i.e. potential passengers). The core of it involves a modified proof-of-work system that requires participants to solve a computational geometry problem called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fixed-radius_near_neighbors&#34;&gt;fixed radius near neighbor problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please bear in mind that &lt;strong&gt;this is only an incomplete, conceptual framework&lt;/strong&gt;. There are likely several challenges and issues with this framework, but I’m hoping it can inspire better and even more viable iterations or solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For La’Zooz’s drive-sharing system to work properly, the creators have suggested that 100,000 people need to have the app open at the same time in approximately the same place. Because of this, it would make sense that the mining system involve the density of, and distance between, Zooz users within a certain defined area. By starting to think about interactions between multiple “Zoozers”, we open the door for potential consensus mechanisms that do not solely rely on the self-reported movement metrics of a single driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than reward drivers based solely off of movement metrics, why not incorporate those metrics into a proof-of-work scheme? Bitcoin uses a proof-of-work mechanism that, at its core, involves miners deriving a hash below a target threshold. The lower the target threshold, the greater the mining difficulty. Conversely, the higher the threshold is, the lower the mining difficulty is. In the case of La’Zooz, we can use a more geometrically-based scheme that involves finding solutions to the aforementioned &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fixed-radius_near_neighbors&#34;&gt;fixed-radius near neighbors problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s take a step back and examine the drive-sharing environment. We have two kinds of entities: moving entities and stationary entities. Moving entities are drivers and stationary entities are “riders” who are looking for a ride. All entities in the drive-sharing network are connected through some kind of P2P protocol and can use public-key cryptography to sign messages containing information about themselves, including GPS coordinates, elevation or altitude, and other miscellaneous data. Each entity has the capacity to broadcast such messages through some or all of the network (perhaps with the aid of a distributed hash table). Finally, we can use a mechanism similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Block_timestamp&#34;&gt;Bitcoin’s block timestamp&lt;/a&gt; to allow the network to come to a consensus on current time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally, each entity will broadcast a signed message with their GPS location data to all other entities in the network. Other entities will keep these messages around only if the GPS locations are within a certain, standardized distance &amp;reg; of themselves. Even then, such messages will only be held for a certain time period (TP) before being discarded. This helps prevent data cache bloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stationary user–or potential rider looking for a ride–can trigger what I will call a “mining challenge” to nearby drivers. To begin the mining challenge, the rider starts identifying nearby drivers (by their signed GPS messages) within a given radius &amp;reg;. R initially starts out as zero. R will increase, until the density of drivers within the given R reaches a Target Density Value (TDV). TDV is something that may be hardcoded into all La’Zooz clients. For reasons that will be clearer in subsequent paragraphs, this system involving TDV can allow mining “difficulty” to increase or decrease depending on the TDV:R ratio. The idea is that in areas with fewer drivers (D), the TDV is achieved with a larger R and low D. However, in areas with many drivers, TDV is reached with low R and high D.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the TDV is reached, the rider can broadcast a Mining Challenge Request (MCR) to all the drivers within R. The MCR includes the semantic IDs and public keys of all drivers within R of the rider (based on previous signed GPS messages). For a challenge to begin, each driver in the cluster must broadcast another signed message to all other potential participants indicating they agree to the challenge. This message (and every message) includes the GPS and elevation location data of the driver. These messages may also include a hash or hashes of all previous messages received as part of the MCR process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once everyone agrees and is in consensus, each driver in the cluster continues to sign and broadcast their location data to all others for a short period of time (maybe few minutes). After this time period has elapsed, the rider can use a heuristic of their choice to see if the GPS position history indicates that the other parties are actual drivers navigating real nearby terrain (e.g. mountains or city grid, etc.) at a given velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the rider is satisfied that all drivers are not cheating, he can prepare to issue the actual challenge, which will make use of the following pieces of data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most recently recorded and signed GPS locations and elevations of all drivers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The GPS location and elevation of the rider, who is at the center of the cluster (based on initially reported locations).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The original cluster radius &amp;reg;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The current network timestamp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: To more fully decentralize the system, you could alternatively use a “consensus triangulation” system, where each entity in the cluster uses position information from other entities to confirm approximate locations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual challenge will be to solve a computational geometry problem called the “fixed-radius, near neighbor problem.” (FRNNP) In this problem, we have as input a set of points in d-dimensional Euclidean space and a fixed distance, delta. One must design a data structure that, given a query point q, efficiently reports the points of the data structure that are within distance delta of q. In our case, d = 3 (since we are using three-dimensional space). Our query point, q, are the (GPS + elevation) coordinates of the rider. Our delta is R, the aforementioned radius. And the other points are the locations of all other drivers in the cluster. Before issuing the challenge, the rider will add a small, random perturbation to the position data to prevent anyone from getting a head start. In addition, the challenge can potentially implement a time limitation system so it is only ephemerally valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, back to our rider. The rider now issues the prepared and finalized time-stamped FRNNP challenge to all the other participating drivers in the cluster. Depending on the number of entities in the cluster (which could eventually be quite large, depending on popularity and density of the network), you can use different solution methods with varying efficacies. Some take advantage of GPUs (such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rchoetzlein.com/fluids3/?page_id=15&#34;&gt;counting sort&lt;/a&gt; method used by Fluids v.3). The framework would have to be tweaked such that the solution was still solvable by mobile computing devices in relatively reasonable amounts of time (few seconds to few minutes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whoever solves the problem first submits the verifiable, timestamped solution to all other entities in the cluster (including the rider). A token reward is now made tentatively available to the driver. However to finalize this transaction, the driver needs to come and pick up the rider. If the rider verifies that the driver picks him up, he can sign a message indicating as such. In addition, a certain proportion of the cluster (perhaps 50%) of non-winning drivers could additionally trace the location of driver and rider to ensure they are traveling together. In this case, if they are satisfied, they can digitally sign and share their approval. There should be a mechanism that rewards non-winning drivers with a (possibly much) smaller reward for helping to verify the winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, ultimately, the mining reward could be a partial (or potentially full) payment for the subsequent ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Series of transactions could be chained together (by including the hash of previous cluster interactions) and completed challenges could be posted to a more permanent blockchain ledger (either a separate one, or perhaps through Bitcoin via a sidechain or treechain mechanism, etc.). Such a chaining and blockchain recording mechanism would certainly need to be thought through more, but the idea is that such a blockchain could be used for disputes. Series of hashed consensus approval messages could be included, but the history should be recorded such that to “modify” it you would have to recompute all the previous challenges (which could ultimately number in the millions or more if the service becomes popular).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, there you have it, my off-the-cuff framework for a drive-sharing reward system using “geometric” proof-of-work! I hope these ideas inspire others to develop more well thought-out systems that take advantage of physical location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;addendum&#34;&gt;Addendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a possible alternative to the fixed-radius, near neighbor problem, you could consider creating some kind of challenge based off of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Three-body_problem#n-body_problem&#34;&gt;n-body problem&lt;/a&gt;, where each moving entity in the cluster is modeled as a particle.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Evolutionary Nomad&#39; Ladder to Success</title>
      <link>http://brandoff.is/blog/the-evolutionary-nomad-ladder-to-success/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 10:40:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brandoff.is/blog/the-evolutionary-nomad-ladder-to-success/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://brandoff.is/img/misty-peaks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The misty peaks of Krabi, Thailand. (Credit: Vyacheslav Argenberg)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-road-to-success-is-dead-long-live-the-roads-to-success&#34;&gt;The road to success is dead. Long live the &lt;em&gt;roads&lt;/em&gt; to success.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2012, The Wall Street Journal announced that Goldman Sachs would be &lt;a href=&#34;http://online.wsj.com/news/articles/SB10000872396390443524904577649830558256586&#34;&gt;scaling back its junior analyst program&lt;/a&gt;. Two year contracts for college grads? Gone. A bonus for completing the program? Nope. For a generation, these analyst positions were a secure first step onto the ladder of success for many financial graduates. Not anymore. Thanks to ongoing global financial turmoil, the times, they are a changin’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s really changing, however, is much, much, bigger than a faltering economy. We are witnessing a cultural phase shift. Or, more specifically, a shift in our cultural metaphors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For better or worse, the metaphors we accept shape our reality. One particularly limiting metaphor is the idea of linear success. You’ll find it hidden in plain sight in phrases such as, “the road to success,” “the ladder of success,” “climbing the corporate ladder,” or even, “the peak of success.” Success is a singular, idealized state at the end of a long road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem is, it doesn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The financial tumult of the past several years is just the latest tremor in an earthquake that has crumbled many traditional “paths to success” and shaken loose our confidence in the linear metaphor. Now that it’s gone, what will replace it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fitness landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born from the field of evolutionary biology, the “fitness landscape” will become the metaphor that opens our minds to the multidimensional nature of success. But what is a fitness landscape?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine for a moment that you are a bartender in a dive bar that only serves vodka with two mixers in 3-ounce glasses. You’re a nice guy, so you’ll make sure each customer gets at least 1 ounce of vodka. This leaves 2 ounces for you to fill with mixers. You can use 2 ounces of one mixer, 2 ounces of the other mixer, or any combination thereof. Some combinations will be tastier than others, and some will be downright disgusting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your quest to create the tastiest (or most optimal) drink, despite your limited resources, you try hundreds of different combinations and come up with an objective taste scale to rate your concoctions against. Better tasting mixes receive higher ratings than poorer ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you have all this data, you want to see if there are any patterns, so you sit down at your computer and start plotting your data on a graph. The x- and y-axes correspond to the amounts of each mixer you used (ranging between 0 and 2 ounces), and the z-axis corresponds to the rating of the combination on your taste scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you may find is that mixer combinations with better taste ratings will appear as “higher” peaks than combinations with lower taste ratings. A number of peaks and valleys appear, corresponding to the ratings or “fitnesses” of each combination. Voilà, you’ve just created a fitness landscape!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://brandoff.is/img/fitness-landscape.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Artistic representation of a 3D graph with &amp;#39;peaks&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;valleys&amp;#39;. (Credit: Patrick Haney)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the world of evolutionary optimization, fitness landscapes are used to solve all sorts of problems, from finding the most streamline shape for an airplane wing, to optimizing supply chains for maximal efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For really complex problems, it can be tough to visualize this landscape in such a way that you can easily discern the highest peaks. This is where the “evolutionary” part comes in. Using computer programs, scientists can send out a sort of “scouting party” by testing several combinations of random parameters (a tiny fraction of all the possible combinations). Using special algorithms–inspired by evolutionary processes found in nature–the best performing “scouts” are selected, and a new generation of scouts is generated based on variations of the successful parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After several generations, the variation between the generations may stabilize, indicating the scouts have converged upon a peak of “relative optimality.” I say relative, because it is quite possible there are other, higher, more “optimal” peaks out there in the fitness landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what the heck does this have to do with us, in the real world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can imagine our linear paths as well-trodden routes up a few local peaks. We are so focused on the road ahead that we don’t see the enormous fitness landscape stretching out beyond us in all directions. Of course, if we only look down, we become abnormally sensitive to the fluctuations and tremors in this one road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time has come to look up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike computer programs, our lives and realities are defined by countless parameters with infinite variations. Rather than stay anchored to one path on one hill, we must wander the landscape and constantly search for new peaks of success and new peaks of experience. Once we see this vast landscape for what it is, we will never let the crumbling of one path or one dead end defeat us. As we make choices and summit each peak, a new vista will open before us and new peaks will emerge from the mist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happen to know a nomad who is already making this journey. [Her name and some details of her story will be changed to respect her privacy].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my close friends from college–let’s call her Anna–was all set to follow in the footsteps of her parents, both of whom are successful executives. She was a top student and was about to enter a prestigious business program when, like many graduates, she experienced a moment of doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this the right career path for me? Is this really what I want to do with the rest of my life? Will I be happy doing something else? How will I know if I’m making the right choice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anna’s education and culture trained her to believe that success meant following a set of culturally acceptable paths to culturally acceptable professions. She was taught that if she left the path, she would be settling for a mediocre existence and always wonder what could have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, after an emotional exchange with her family, she took the next flight to Thailand and embarked on the most exciting adventure of her life. In the past four years she’s traveled across Asia, received an online master’s degree in teaching, and married a fellow expatriate that she encountered along her journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anna now sees that for each path of “success,” each choice that she turns down, an innumerable number of new paths open up, taking her to peaks she could never have dreamed of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to become an expatriate to reap the benefits of the “fitness landscape” mindset. All you need to remember is that there is no such thing as a singular “road to success.” Most “ladders to success” are leaning against a few, overcrowded peaks. You know better now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t settle. Always keep moving. You never know what’s just beyond the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>